<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bl-mc.se/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://bl-mc.se/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-20T22:14:11+01:00</updated><id>https://bl-mc.se/feed.xml</id><title type="html">BL Monitor &amp;amp; Control</title><subtitle>Accelerating the commercialization of compact particle accelerators through fully integrated, ready to go subsystems</subtitle><author><name>Georg Hulla</name></author><entry><title type="html">Compact Mode 0 beam stabilization system</title><link href="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/17/mode0-beam-stabilization-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compact Mode 0 beam stabilization system" /><published>2024-11-17T15:45:13+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T15:45:13+01:00</updated><id>https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/17/mode0-beam-stabilization-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/17/mode0-beam-stabilization-system.html"><![CDATA[<p><b><i>Place of installation:</i></b> <a href="https://www.maxiv.lu.se/">MAX IV</a> laboratory in Lund/Sweden</p>

<p><b><i>Background:</i></b> Many of the latest generation light sources are transitioning to long bunch operation to dramatically improve beam brightness. However, most particle accelerator bunch lengthening systems inherently introduce instabilities that can severely impact beam brightness.</p>

<p><b><i>Implementation:</i></b> A compact Mode 0 beam stabilization system based on incorporating the Red Pitaya Stemlab 125-14LN into the Blinky-Lite platform has been commissioned at MAX IV. The system enables long bunch operation at high beam intensities with record beam brightness.</p>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-17/Mode0_first.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">First version of the Mode 0 beam stabilization system at the heart of MAX IV, doubling its beam brightness.</span>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-17/Mode0_advanced.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Advanced version - FPGA code, hardware and user applications.</span>

<p><b><i>Benefit:</i></b> In long bunch mode, which is needed for a bright beam, MAX IV was previously limited to under 125mA but thanks to the beam stabilization system is now operating at 400 mA. The Red Pitaya Mode 0 system has been operating for over a year without causing any down-time to the accelerator.</p>

<p><b><i>Our offering:</i></b>  The compact Mode 0 beam stabilization system can be easily integrated in almost any other light source.</p>]]></content><author><name>Georg Hulla</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Place of installation: MAX IV laboratory in Lund/Sweden]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wireless leak detection system</title><link href="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/10/wireless-leak-detection-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wireless leak detection system" /><published>2024-11-10T15:45:13+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T15:45:13+01:00</updated><id>https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/10/wireless-leak-detection-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/10/wireless-leak-detection-system.html"><![CDATA[<p><b><i>Place of installation:</i></b> <a href="https://www.maxiv.lu.se/">MAX IV</a> laboratory in Lund/Sweden</p>

<p><b><i>Background:</i></b> Water leaks pose significant risks to particle accelerators because they can cause electrical short circuits, damage sensitive equipment, contaminate vacuum systems, and disrupt thermal regulation. Leaks may also spread radioactive material from activated components, complicating cleanup and increasing personal hazards. Such incidents lead to costly repairs, facility downtime, and safety risks to personnel. Preventive measures like leak detection systems are crucial to safeguard the reliability of such facilities.</p>

<p>For preventive measures, the MAX IV computer server rooms as well as the 520 meter synchrotron ring had to be equipped with leak detectors. The <i>challenge</i> was to do this with the least possible impact to the already existing facility infrastructure (i.e. avoiding to pull new control cables).</p>

<p><b><i>Implementation:</i></b> Fourteen wireless Blinky-Leak boxes, each of them able to read two 20 meter long sectors, comprise the system. The complete system was installed by one person in less than 3 weeks and is operational and connected to the MAX IV notification system since fall 2023 (see live <a href="https://bl-maxiv.se/myapps?external">system</a>).</p>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-10/Sensor_electronics.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Blinky-Leak boxes electronics design.</span>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-10/Sensor_installation.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Leak detector installation at MAX IV.</span>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-10/User_app.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Leak detector mobile user applications and alarm screens.</span>

<p><b><i>Benefit:</i></b> Proactive leak prevention at MAX IV.</p>

<p>Example: On Friday 5-July 2024, the Blinky-Lite water leak detector system at MAX IV sent out a notification that there was a leak in Sector 14. On Monday 8-July, the repair crew found a cooling hose leaking in Sector 14 and promptly repaired it.</p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-10/R3LeakDetection2024_07.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Leak detection system detecting leak at MAX IV. Alarm screen and user app.</span>

<p><b><i>Our offering:</i></b> A wireless leak detection systems, that</p>
<li>can determine leak locations to within a few meters or less</li>
<li>notifies users of water leaks</li>
<li>alarms users on detector fault and communication failure</li>]]></content><author><name>Georg Hulla</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Place of installation: MAX IV laboratory in Lund/Sweden]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Complete RFQ control system</title><link href="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/03/rfq-control-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Complete RFQ control system" /><published>2024-11-03T15:45:13+01:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T15:45:13+01:00</updated><id>https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/03/rfq-control-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bl-mc.se/2024/11/03/rfq-control-system.html"><![CDATA[<p><b><i>Place of installation:</i></b> <a href="https://mirrotron.com/en">Mirrotron</a> laboratory in Martonvásár/Hungary</p>

<p><b><i>Background:</i></b> The Mirrotron Radio Frequency Quadrupole (RFQ) is part of a compact neutron source that is being built in Martonvásár Hungary.</p>

<p>The 2.5 MeV RFQ designed and built by Time Co, Ltd., Japan is a pulsed accelerator that can support 1.25 mS pulses at a rate of 40 Hz for a maximum duty factor of 5% . The RFQ can accelerate a peak beam current of 20 mA with an input RF power 260 kW at 200 MHz. providing an average beam power of 2.5 kW. The loaded cavity Q is 10,000 which results in a cavity bandwidth of 20 kHz.</p>

<p>The RFQ accelerator system can be divided into 5 major subsystems</p>
<li>RF source (LLRF)</li>
<li>Timing system</li>
<li>200 MHz RF power amplifier</li>
<li>Vacuum system</li>
<li>Cooling system</li>

<p><b><i>Implementation:</i></b> (a more detailed description of the control system can be found <a href="https://bl-mirrotron.github.io/">here</a>).</p>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-03/Mode0_first.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Capture</span>

<p></p>

<img class="img-fluid" src="/img/posts/2024-11-03/Mode0_advanced.jpg" alt="Demo Image">
<span class="caption text-muted">Capture</span>

<p><b><i>Benefit:</i></b> </p>

<p><b><i>Our offering:</i></b> A complete RFQ control system consisting of the above mentioned subsystems.</p>]]></content><author><name>Georg Hulla</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Place of installation: Mirrotron laboratory in Martonvásár/Hungary]]></summary></entry></feed>